Register of the Okhrana records
Hoover Institution Archives
- XVII. Revolutionary leaders (Boxes 196-205, 242)
  - a. Vladimir Il'ich Lenin and Nadezhda Konstantinovna Krupskaya (Boxes 196-197)
    - Report on the split among the "Iskrovtsy,", 1904 (Index XVIIa, Folder 2c)
    - Excerpt from a letter from Lenin in Geneva to his mother in Kiev, 1904 (Index XVIIa, Folder 2d)
      Includes an English translation
    - Report on "Katia" Krupsakaya as an important member of Iskra, 1904 (Index XVIIa, Folder 2e)
    - Letter from Lenin, Zverev, and Glebov in Darmstadt to Dauge in Moscow, 1904 (Index XVIIa, Folder 2f)
    - Letter from Lenin in Nuremberg to Dr. Aleksandrov in Gomel, 1904 (Index XVIIa, Folder 2g)
    - Letter from Krupskaya in Nuremberg to Shpolianskaia in Moscow, 1904 (Index XVIIa, Folder 2h)
    - Letter from Lenin to Anton Peres in Moscow, 1904 (Index XVIIa, Folder 2i)
    - Letter from Lenin in Nuremberg to Sokolovskii in Odessa, 1904 (Index XVIIa, Folder 2j)
    - Dispatch from Headquarters advising that Bogdanov is giving financial help to Lenin, 1905 (Index XVIIa, Folder 2k)
    - Report on the 3rd London RSDWP Congress and Lenin's role, 1905 (Index XVIIa, Folder 2l)
    - Letter from Krupskaya in Leipzig to Vera Mikler in Moscow, 1905 (Index XVIIa, Folder 2m)
    - Letter from Lenin in Munich to Pushenskii, 1905 (Index XVIIa, Folder 2n)
    - Letter from Lenin in Munich to Pushenskii in Kherson (with English translation), 1905 (Index XVIIa, Folder 2o)
    - Report on the Social Democratic Conference in Vyborg and Lenin's role, 1906 (Index XVIIa, Folder 2p)
    - Letter from Krupskaya to Lenin (Index XVIIa, Folder 2q)
    - Report on the All-Russian Conference of the Social Democratic Party in Paris, 1909 (Index XVIIa, Folder 2r)
    - Roster of the members of the RSDWP-Bolshevik faction abroad, 1909 (Index XVIIa, Folder 2s)
    - Letter from Moscow to Krupskaya containing the texts of agitation pamphlets, 1909 (Index XVIIa, Folder 2t)
    - Letter from Lenin in Paris to his sister in Russia discussing peace with the Mensheviks, 1910 (Index XVIIa, Folder 2u)
    - Report on the composition of the RSDWP Central Committee including Lenin, 1910 (Index XVIIa, Folder 2v)
    - Letter from Lenin in Paris to I. K. Frim in Bucharest, 1911 (Index XVIIa, Folder 2w)
    - Letter from Krupskaya in Paris to Iukevich in St. Petersburg, 1911 (Index XVIIa, Folder 2x)
    - Report on Lenin's attempts to sue Tsetkina for 80,000 francs, an inheritance left by Schmidt, 1911 (Index XVIIa, Folder 2y)
    - Memorandum from Headquarters reporting on a conference of Lenin's political partisans, 1912 (Index XVIIa, Folder 2z)
    - Report on Lenin and Zinovyev (Grigorii Radomysl'skii) moving to Krakow to be closer to Russia during the Duma elections, 1912 (Index XVIIa, Folder 3a)
    - Letters from Lenin in Krakow to the Pravda editorial office in St. Petersburg, 1912 (Index XVIIa, Folder 3b-3e)
    - Letter from Krupskaya in Krakow to Nazarov in St. Petersburg, 1912 (Index XVIIa, Folder 3f)
    - Letter from Lenin in Krakow to the editorial office of Sovremennyi mir in St. Petersberg, 1912 (Index XVIIa, Folder 3g)
    - Letter from Krupskaya to Akselrod in St. Petersburg, 1912 (Index XVIIa, Folder 3h-3k)
    - Letter from Krupskaya to Podvoiskii in St. Petersburg (Index XVIIa, Folder 3l-3m)
    - Letter from Lenin in Krakow to the Pravda editorial office in St. Petersburg, 1913 (Index XVIIa, Folder 3n-3o)
    - Letter from Lenin in Krakow to Lazurkin in St. Petersburg, 1913 (Index XVIIa, Folder 3p)
    - Letter from Lenin in Krakow to Bel'skii in St. Petersburg, 1913 (Index XVIIa, Folder 3q)
    - Letters from Krupskaya in Krakow to Podvoiskii in St. Petersburg, 1913 (Index XVIIa, Folder 3r-3u)
    - Letters from Lenin in Krakow to his sister Mariia in Saratov, 1913 (Index XVIIa, Folder 3v)
    - Letter from Krupskaya in Krakow to Kvaleva in St. Petersburg, 1913 (Index XVIIa, Folder 3w)
    - Letter from Krupskaya in Krakow to Podvoiskii in St. Petersburg, 1913 (Index XVIIa, Folder 3x)
    - Letter from Krupskaya in Krakow to Knipovich in St. Petersburg, 1913 (Index XVIIa, Folder 3y)
    - Letter from Krupskaya in Krakow to Rymash in St. Petersburg, 1913 (Index XVIIa, Folder 3z)
    - Letter from Krupskaya in Zakopane to Kvaleva in St. Petersburg, 1913 (Index XVIIa, Folder 4a)
    - Letter from Krupskaya in Zakopane to Podvoiskii in St. Petersburg, 1913 (Index XVIIa, Folder 4b)
    - Letter from Lenin in Zakopane to Podvoiskii in St. Petersburg (Index XVIIa, Folder 4b)
    - Letter from Lenin in Zakopane to Kolkov in St. Petersburg (Index XVIIa, Folder 4c)
    - Letter from Lenin in Zakopane to Podvoiskii in St. Petersburg, 1913 (Index XVIIa, Folder 4d)
    - Letter from Lenin in Krakow to Pravda editorial office in St. Petersburg, 1913 (Index XVIIa, Folder 4e)
    - Letter from Krupskaya in Krakow to Sekorskii in Tiflis, 1913 (Index XVIIa, Folder 4f)
    - Letter from Krupskaya in Krakow to Kavtaradze in St. Petersburg, 1913 (Index XVIIa, Folder 4g)
    - Letter from Krupskaya in Krakow to Za pravdu in St. Petersburg, 1913 (Index XVIIa, Folder 4h)
    - Letter from Krupskaya in Krakow to Samolei in St. Petersburg reporting on the strike movement, 1913 (Index XVIIa, Folder 4i)
    - Report on the 2nd Regular Conference of the RSDWP and Lenin's role, 1913 (Index XVIIa, Folder 4j)
    - Letter from Krupskaya in Krakow to Antoshevskaia in Viatka, 1913 (Index XVIIa, Folder 4k)
    - Letter from Krupskaya in Krakow to Elizarova in St. Petersburg, 1914 (Index XVIIa, Folder 4l)
    - Letter from Krupskaya in Krakow to Anton Samolei in St. Petersburg, 1914 (Index XVIIa, Folder 4m)
    - Letter from Krupskaya in Krakow to Nina Krug in St. Petersburg, 1914 (Index XVIIa, Folder 4n)
    - Letter from Krupskaya in Krakow to Voitsekhovskii in St. Petersburg, 1914 (Index XVIIa, Folder 4o)
    - Letter from Krupskaya in Vienna to Sikorskii in Tiflis regarding preparations for a congress, 1914 (Index XVIIa, Folder 4p)
    - Letter from Krupskaya in Zakopane to Proveshchenie in St. Petersburg on the 2rd International Conference of Women Socialists and Female Workers' Organizations, 1914 (Index XVIIa, Folder 4q)
    - Letter from Krupskaya in Rabka to Ivan Samovarov, 1914 (Index XVIIa, Folder 4r)
    - Letter from Krupskaya in Poronin to Enukidze in St. Petersburg asking for information on Georgian and Armenian newspapers published in the Caucasus, 1914 (Index XVIIa, Folder 4s)
    - Letter from Krupskaya in Austria to Ivan Samovarov in Kremlevo Station, 1914 (Index XVIIa, Folder 4t)
    - Report advising that Lenin is not in prison in Krakow, but is living in Berlin, 1914 (Index XVIIa, Folder 4u)
    - Letter from Lenin's sister Mariia in Petrograd to Lenin in Bern containing family news, 1915 (Index XVIIa, Folder 4v)
      Includes English translation.
    - Report on Lenin's attitude towards terrorism, 1916 (Index XVIIa, Folder 4w)
    - Briefs on Safarov, relative of Krupskaya, Ludmila Stiglis and Selikmann, 1915 (Index XVIIa, Folder 4x)
    - Report on Lenin's defeatist views regarding Russia's participation in the war, 1915 (Index XVIIa, Folder 4y)
    - Letters in French by or about Lenin, 1916 (Index XVIIa, Folder 4z)
    - Lenin's letter to Safarov in French, 1916 (Index XVIIa, Folder 5a)
      Available on microfilm reel 358
    - Chronological review of Lenin's activities from February 1904-April 1916 (Index XVIIa, Folder 5b)
    - Surveillance reports on Lenin by agent Bint, 1915-1916 (Index XVIIa, Folder 5c)
    - Report on Lenin's lecture, "Conditions of Peace and the National Question,", 1916 (Index XVIIa, Folder 5d)
    - Resume of Lenin's report in Zurich entitled "The War and Two Internationals,", 1916 (Index XVIIa, Folder 5e)
    - Statements by Lenin to Safarov on French revolutionaries, 1916 (Index XVIIa, Folder 5f)
    - Resume of a lecture delivered by Lenin in Geneva entitled "Two Currents in the International Workers' Movement,", 1916 (Index XVIIa, Folder 5g)
    - Report on the Geneva Conference of émigré Treasuries, with Krupskaya as secretary, 1917 (Index XVIIa, Folder 5h)
    - Cable about Lenin receiving the protection of Germany, 1916 (Index XVIIa, Folder 5i)
    - Report on Lenin's participation in the Bern Conference of International Socialist Commissions, 1917 (Index XVIIa, Folder 5j)
    - Draft of a declaration to be published by the RSDWP Central Committee (represented by Lenin) on the conference of socialists of the "concordat" countries, 1917 (Index XVIIa, Folder 5k)
    - Report on existing opinion on Lenin's attitude towards terror, 1917 (Index XVIIa, Folder 5l)
    - Report concerning Lenin's mistress Inessa Armand, 1917 (Index XVIIa, Folder 5m)
    - Okhrana circular on Nadezhda Krupskaya (Index XVIIa, Folder 5n)
    - Safarov's letters to Krupskaya, 1915-1916 (Index XVIIa, Folder 5o)
    - English translations of Lenin's correspondence (Index XVIIa, Folder 5p)
    - Cross-reference sheet (Index XVIIa, Folder 6)
    - Reference: For agent Zhitomirskii's (Daudet) reports on Lenin and his group from 1911-1913, see IIIf, folder 36 (Index XVIIa, Folder 7)
    - Reference: See agent Bint's 1917 report on Inessa Armand in VIk, folder 5 (Index XVIIa, Folder 8)
    - Reference: See intelligence summary no. 61, 1903, on Anichkin, a student in St. Petersburg, involved in a plot with Lenin in XIIIc(2), folder 2 (Index XVIIa, Folder 9)
    - Reference: See outgoing telegram no. 224, January 9, 1916, advising that Lenin's courier "Liza" is departing Switzerland for Russia, in XIIIb(2), folder 8 (Index XVIIa, Folder 10)
  - b. Georgii Valentinovich Plekhanov (Box 197)
    The collection of papers on this Marxist theoretician, founder of the Russian Social Democratic Party, and comrade and opponent of Lenin, dates from 1891 to 19l6. Folder 1 contains an assortment of various dispatches, while the documents in Folder 2, individually described, refer to his various activities, organizational work, funding, extraditions, and differences with the Bolshevik faction of the Party. Of considerable interest are the intercepted letters. As later with Lenin, Plekhanov had troubles with P. Lavrov, the anarchist leader in London. Also includes Headquarters circulars giving Plekhanov's physical description and photograph.
    - Various dispatches referring to Plekhanov, 1894-1916 (Index XVIIb, Folder 1)
    - French surveillance agent reports on Plekhanov, 1891 (Index XVIIb, Folder 2a)
    - Letters on Plekhanov and his work, 1892 (Index XVIIb, Folder 2b)
    - Plans of the French government to deport Plekhanov and Selikrevskii, 1894 (Index XVIIb, Folder 2c)
    - Report that Plekhanov still visits Geneva, 1894 (Index XVIIb, Folder 2d)
    - Plekhanov's intention to withdraw from the Party, 1905 (Index XVIIb, Folder 2e)
    - Views of the Kostroma Committee regarding Plekhanov's desire to represent the Party at the International Socialist Bureau, 1905 (Index XVIIb, Folder 2f)
    - Letter from Smirnov to Plekhanov in Geneva about Deutsch and Zasulich, 1906 (Index XVIIb, Folder 2g)
    - Letter regarding a financial contribution for Plekhanov, 1909 (Index XVIIb, Folder 2h)
    - Okhrana's circular on Plekhanov with his photograph, 1909 (Index XVIIb, Folder 2i)
    - Physical description of Plekhanov, 1912 (Index XVIIb, Folder 2j)
    - Report that Burtsev and Plekhanov are planning to go to Russia, 1912 (Index XVIIb, Folder 2k)
    - Plekhanov's letter on preparations for the Duma elections, 1912 (Index XVIIb, Folder 2l)
    - Plekhanov's letter on non-recognition of Lenin's Central Committee as the central organization of the Party, 1912 (Index XVIIb, Folder 2m)
    - Report that Plekhanov enrolled in electricians' school in Paris, 1912 (Index XVIIb, Folder 2n)
    - Report that Plekhanov arrived in Paris to organize a meeting of the conciliatory faction, 1912 (Index XVIIb, Folder 2o)
    - Letter to Plekhanov concerning the "liquidation" theory and other party theories, 1913 (Index XVIIb, Folder 2p)
    - Lecture delivered by Plekhanov on "The National Question and the Social Democrats,", 1914 (Index XVIIb, Folder 2q)
    - Lecture entitled "War and the Social Democracy" delivered by Plekhanov in Lausanne, 1914 (Index XVIIb, Folder 2r)
    - Report on the publication Edinstvo by Plekhanov, 1914 (Index XVIIb, Folder 2s)
    - Dispatches concerning the whereabouts of Plekhanov, 1916 (Index XVIIb, Folder 2t)
    - Background and activities report on Plekhanov (Index XVIIb, Folder 2u)
    - Cross-reference sheet (Index XVIIb, Folder 3)
  - c. Leon Trotsky (Box 197)
    The collection in Folder 1 covers the period from 1901 to 1917. The intercepted letters of Natalia and Lev Bronstein and those of Trotsky's wife are of particular interest, pertaining mostly to Party matters. Differences and reconciliations with Lenin are referred to in this as well as in individually inventoried documents in the second folder. Correspondence with the Socialists in the Duma, Trotsky's stay in the United States, his travels, and editorial work, particularly on Nashe Slovo are covered. Several Okhrana intercepts and copies include Trotsky's letters.
    - Various dispatches and letters pertaining to Trotsky, 1901-1917 (Index XVIIc, Folder 1)
    - Report on RSDWP member Bronstein in Geneva and his relations with Helfand, 1904 (Index XVIIc, Folder 2a)
    - Letters from "Sasha" in St. Petersburg to her husband Trotsky in Vienna, 1908-1910 (Index XVIIc, Folder 2b)
    - Letter from Trotsky in Kiev to de Montbrand in Lausanne, 1909 (Index XVIIc, Folder 2c)
    - Data on Trotsky's wife, 1910 (Index XVIIc, Folder 2d)
    - Letter from Trotsky in Vienna to Duma deputy Pokrovskii, 1910 (Index XVIIc, Folder 2e)
    - Report of the Nikolaevsk Okhrana chief on Trotsky, his wife, and other revolutionaries, 1912 (Index XVIIc, Folder 2f)
    - Report of the Odessa Okhrana chief on Trotsky and his wife, 1912 (Index XVIIc, Folder 2g)
    - Letters from an unidentified writer to Akselrod in Zurich and Trotsky in Vienna on the German Social Democratic Party conference, 1913 (Index XVIIc, Folder 2h)
    - Letter from Trotsky in Vienna to the editor of Luch, 1913 (Index XVIIc, Folder 2i)
    - Trotsky's letter to Duma member Chkheidze praising his speeches and commenting on Leninism, 1913 (Index XVIIc, Folder 2j)
    - Report that Trotsky arrived in Paris, 1914 (Index XVIIc, Folder 2k)
    - Trotsky's speech in Paris on "The Defense of the Homeland,", 1915 (Index XVIIc, Folder 2l)
    - Trotsky's speech in a workers' club in Paris, 1915 (Index XVIIc, Folder 2m)
    - Bint's report on Trotsky's activities, 1915 (Index XVIIc, Folder 2n)
    - Report on Chernov and Trotsky touring Switzerland and agitating for the cessation of the war, 1915 (Index XVIIc, Folder 2o)
    - Report on the pro-German stance of Trotsky's newspaper Nashe slovo, 1915 (Index XVIIc, Folder 2p)
    - Bint's report revealing Trotsky as an Austrian agent, 1916 (Index XVIIc, Folder 2q)
    - Meeting of the Committee for the Resumption of International Relations and Trotsky's role in it, 1916 (Index XVIIc, Folder 2r)
    - Documents pertaining to the deportation of Trotsky from France, 1916 (Index XVIIc, Folder 2s)
    - Documents pertaining to Trotsky's efforts to obtain a Swiss visa, 1916 (Index XVIIc, Folder 2t)
    - Moscow millionaire Shakhov's offer of financial assistance to Trotsky, 1916 (Index XVIIc, Folder 2u)
    - Agent Bint's reports on Trotsky, 1916 (Index XVIIc, Folder 2v)
    - Letter from Trotsky to his friends in New York, 1917 (Index XVIIc, Folder 2w)
    - Arrival of Trotsky and his family in New York, 1917 (Index XVIIc, Folder 2x)
    - Report on Trotsky as the editor of Nashe slovo (Index XVIIc, Folder 2y)
    - Official Okhrana circulars on Trotsky (Index XVIIc, Folder 2z)
    - Cross-reference sheet (Index XVIIc, Folder 3)
    - Reference: See reports on Trotsky's daily newspaper Nashe slovo and on the polemics of its banning, in XVIIr(1) (Index XVIIc, Folder 4)
    - Reference: See report on Nashe slovo for 1916, banned as being pro-German, in VIIIb, folder 3 (Index XVIIc, Folder 5)
  - d. Vladimir L'vovich Burtsev (Boxes 197-198)
    This extensive collection is the most telling proof that Vladimir Burtsev and his work represented a continuous and important target for the Okhrana in Paris. A competent writer, propagandist, and advocate of terror and assassination as a means leading to revolution, he developed also an active revolutionary counter-intelligence with the purpose of exposing Okhrana agents and discrediting the Okhrana as an establishment in European countries. In this connection, many of the documents concerning Burtsev are also located under XXIVa and XXIVb, since the bulk of revolutionary intelligence and propaganda was either directed by Burtsev or closely affiliated with his functions.
    Folder 1, in two sections, contains general materials of Burtsev, dispatches on him and his writings, copies of intercepted letters, various agent reports, etc. His functions and the contributions of Okhrana defector Mikhail Bakai in exposing Evno Azef are well covered, as is also Burtsev's exposure of Okhrana Chief Garting.
    Folders 2 to 5 have documents concentrating on certain periods and events, as for instance, Folder 5, with papers on Burtsev's stay in Rumania and England, his imprisonments in London, and the case of agent Bullier. Folder 3, in two sections, for the period from 1899 to 1917 concentrates on Burtsev's work in Paris, revealing the nature of the revolutionary police and Burtsev's methods of intelligence operations and press campaigns. Surveillance reports on him and his intelligence service are dated from 1906 to 1914.
    Folder 4 covers the Okhrana's attempts to have Burtsev and his group deported from France, while the last folder (No. 5) contains information on his return to Russia, official trial records, intercepted correspondence from the jail, disposal of his archive and personal effects in Paris, etc.
    Available on microfilm reels 359-361
    - Miscellaneous documents including intercepted letters, dispatches, and agent reports pertaining to Burtsev and the defector Mikhail Bakai, 1890-1916 (Index XVIId, Folder 1)
      Available on microfilm reel 359
    - Documents on Burtsev's stay in Romania and England, his arrest and imprisonment in London, and the case against agent Charlotte Bullier, 1890-1899 (Index XVIId, Folder 2)
      Available on microfilm reel 360
    - Collection of papers pertaining to Burtsev's work in Paris; Burtsev's revolutionary police; publication of Budushchee; detailed Okhrana report on his mode of operation; his press campaign against Garting and the Paris Okhrana; collections of surveillance reports on Burtsev; Burtsev's trip to the United States, 1899-1917 (Index XVIId, Folder 3)
      Available on microfilm reels 360-361
    - Dispatches and reports concerning the Okhrana's attempts to have Burtsev deported from France, 1904, 1909 (Index XVIId, Folder 4)
      Available on microfilm reel 361
    - Documents pertaining to Burtsev's imprisonment in Russia: official trial records, intercepted correspondence between the imprisoned Burtsev and Paris concerning the disposition of his personal affairs in Paris, 1914-1915 (Index XVIId, Folder 5)
    - Cross-reference sheet (Index XVIId, Folder 6)
    - Reference: See intelligence summary no. 17, January 24, 1903, regarding Burtsev and Krakov in the Socialist Revolutionary Fighting Unit, in XIIIc(2), folder 2 (Index XVIId, Folder 7)
    - Reference: See intelligence summary no. 42, July 16, 1903, on Burtsev's role in the plot to assassinate the Minister of the Interior, in XIIIc(2), folder 2 (Index XVIId, Folder 8)
    - Reference: See intelligence summary no. 62, December 4, 1903, on Burtsev in England and Switzerland, in XIIIc(2), folder 2 (Index XVIId, Folder 9)
    - Reference: See intelligence summary no. 94, July 15, 1905, concerning Burtsev and Krakov, in XIIIc(2), folder 4 (Index XVIId, Folder 10)
    - Reference: For letters addressed to Burtsev and reports on his accusations against Okhrana censorship and perlustration, see Xc (Index XVIId, Folder 11)
    - Reference: For reports on Jollivet's assignments on Burtsev and Leroy, 1914-1915, see VIk, folder 33 (Index XVIId, Folder 12)
    - Reference: See Charlotte Bullier's personnel file for reports on her contacts with Burtsev, in IIIe, folder 3 (Index XVIId, Folder 13)
    - Reference: See incoming telegram no. 166, January 21, 1903, for instructions concerning surveillance over Krakov between Bern and the Russian border, in XIIIc(3), folder 14 (Index XVIId, Folder 14)
    - Reference: See outgoing telegram, June 2, 1903, informing of a secret courier en route from Burtsev to St. Petersburg, in XIIIb(2), folder 2 (Index XVIId, Folder 15)
    - Reference: See outgoing telegram, November 12, 1903, advising that Burtsev is about to publish the fifth issue of Narodovolets, in XIIIb(2), folder 2 (Index XVIId, Folder 16)
    - Reference: See outgoing telegram, March 23, 1904, advising that Burtsev and Krakov left Paris secretly for an unknown destination, in XIIIb(2), folder 3 (Index XVIId, Folder 17)
    - Reference: See outgoing telegram, June 15, 1904, advising that Burtsev is expecting an event of grave consequences to take place in Russia, in XIIIb(2), folder 3 (Index XVIId, Folder 18)
  - e. Grigory Yevseyevich Zinovyev (Box 198)
    A large number of documents pertain to this important Bolshevik leader, closest associate of Lenin, writer, and orator. However, most of the Okhrana dispatches pertaining to his work and activities deal also with other top revolutionaries and have therefore been placed under various other index numbers. (See the cross-reference sheet in Folder 6. )
    - Letter from Zinovyev in Paris to Mlle. Levin in St. Petersburg about the publication of a magazine, 1910 (Index XVIIe, Folder 1)
    - Letter from Zinovyev in Paris to Duma member Poletaiev regarding the placement of a newspaper announcement, 1910 (Index XVIIe, Folder 2)
    - Zinovyev's brochure "Elections to the Fourth Duma and Our Tasks,", 1911 (Index XVIIe, Folder 3)
    - Report that Zinovyev is in St. Petersburg, 1913 (Index XVIIe, Folder 4)
    - Okhrana circular on the background of Zinovyev ("Radomyslskii") (Index XVIIe, Folder 5)
    - Cross-reference sheet (Index XVIIe, Folder 6)
  - f. Pavel Nikolaevich Miliukov and Aleksandr Fyodorovich Kerensky (Box 198)
    The file on Miliukov consists of dispatches sent by Headquarters to the Paris Office, dating back to 1897 and giving his background and his contacts with Russian revolutionaries abroad. The Paris Office reported twice to Headquarters on Miliukov's comments on conditions which would assure the revolutionaries victory (May 1916) and on his meeting with Bulgarian minister Todorov (December 1916) in Lausanne. Miliukov was representing the Cadet Party in the Third and Fourth Dumas.
    - Background information on Miliukov, 1897 (Index XVIIf, Folder 1a)
    - Letters from Soskis in Paris to Miliukov transmitting a manuscript for publication, 1898 (Index XVIIf, Folder 1b)
    - Dispatch giving background information on Miliukov, 1902 (Index XVIIf, Folder 1c)
    - Letter from Miliukov in London on his plans for a lecture tour of America, 1904 (Index XVIIf, Folder 1d)
    - Memo advising that Miliukov left Russia again, 1904 (Index XVIIf, Folder 1e)
    - Letter from "Shklovskaia" in London to Miliukov in St. Petersburg, 1910 (Index XVIIf, Folder 1f)
    - Newspaper item titled "Les atrocitiés bulgares" on the role of Miliukov, 1913 (Index XVIIf, Folder 1g)
    - Copy of La Courier Européen, co-published by Miliukov, 1914 (Index XVIIf, Folder 1h)
    - On O. Masarik's correspondence with Miliukov, 1915 (Index XVIIf, Folder 1i)
    - Clipping from L'Oeuvre with Miliukov's article, 1916 (Index XVIIf, Folder 1j)
    - Report on Miliukov's meeting with Todorov, 1916 (Index XVIIf, Folder 1k)